Guide to the United Irish Counties Association Records AIA 056
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
United Irish Counties Association
1931-2007
AIA 056
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
3.25 linear feet (4 boxes)
Irish county organizations were first organized in New York City in the late 1840s. The early societies were for the most part purely social organizations, but in the 1870s some of them started to offer benefits for sickness and death. As the Irish settled into different areas of the city, individual County Societies became more prevalent. With the growth of Irish sports, these county societies were even more important. The United Irish Counties Assocation organized in 1904 as an attempt to reunite again all Irish under one umbrella organization. The UICA aims to promote and preserve Irish heritage and culture. Its Annual Feis brings together Irish talent for a celebration of music, dance, and song.
Archives of Irish America.
Arrangement
Files are organized alphabetically. The Annual event seems to have changed names between ball and dance over the years; these files are organized chronologically. Collection is arranged into one series.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Archives of Irish America County Society Records (AIA 003)
James J. Comerford Papers (AIA 010)
Emerald Society Records (AIA 057)
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Irish county organizations were first organized in New York City in the late 1840s. The early societies were for the most part purely social organizations, but in the 1870s some of them started to offer benefits for sickness and death. With the growth of Irish sports, these county societies were even more important. The United Irish Counties Association organized in 1904 as the Irish Counties Athletic Union, as an organization to coordinate and provide venues for sporting events and dances. The goal was to reunite the individual Irish Societies under one umbrella organization, to establish a "central unit of administration to guide and coordinate the activities of the Irish County Organizations," according to the history written by James Comerford, former President of the UICA. (See Box 3, Folder 18.) In 1907, the name was changed to United Irish Counties Association (UICA) with the aim of providing more Irish activities in addition to sports and dances. The purpose of the UICA as set for in its incorporation papers is to: "aid and encourage the members of the Irish race in this State (New York) in taking advantage of all the educational and business opportunities; to furnish information and advice to them on all matters relating to high schools, night schools, trade schools, civil service and commercial opportunities." The organization also promotes activities to preserve and promote the traditional culture if the Irish. This is realized in the Feis, a annual celebration of Irish music, dance, song and athletics.
For more information, visit: http://www.uicany.org/United_Irish_Counties/History.html
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of souvenir journals from the annual dinners and dances of the Association. Also included are programs and documentation on the Feis, a festival celebrating Irish culture and music. A scrapbook kept by Rosalie Fitzpatrick on the Feis is also included in the collection. The unbound scrapbook contains originals and photocopies of many of the Feis programs as well as newspaper clippings and articles. One of the articles is written by Ms. Fitzpatrick herself in response to an article written by a Ms. Miller on the meaning and tradition of the Feis. Also of interest is a history of the UICA written by James Comerford, one-time President of the Association. A copy of the article is contained in Ms. Fitzpatrick's scrapbook (Box 3, Folder 18).
United Irish Counties Association of N.Y.; Feis; Irish Americans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social life and customs.; Souvenir programs.
- Annual Ball: Committee, 1975-1997 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Annual Ball Journal, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Annual Ball Journal, 1954-1967 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Annual Grand Ball Journal, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Annual Grand Ball Journal, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Annual Grand Ball Journal, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Annual Grand Ball Journal, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Annual Grand Ball Journal: Diamond Jubilee, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Annual Grand Ball Journal, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Annual Grand Ball Journal, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Annual Grand Ball Journal, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Annual Grand Ball Journal, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Annual Ball Journal, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Annual Ball Journal, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Annual Ball Journal, 1991, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Annual Dinner Dance Journal, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Annual Dinner Dance Journal, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Annual Dinner Dance Journal, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Annual Dinner Dance Journal, 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Annual Dinner Dance Journal, 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Annual Dinner Dance Journal, 2002-2003 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Annual Dinner Dance Journal, 2004-2005 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Annual Banquet, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Annual Banquet, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Annual Feis: Circulars, 1984-2008 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Annual Feis: Committee, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Annual Feis: Delegates Meeting, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Annual Feis: Documentation, 1951-1984 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Annual Feis: Program, 1942-1950 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Annual Feis: Program, 1952-1962 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Annual Feis: Program, 1963-1972 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Annual Feis: Program, 1981-1985 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Annual Feis: Program, 1986-1988 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Annual Feis: Program, 1996-1997 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Annual Feis: Program, 2002-2003 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Annual Feis: Program, 2005-2006 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Annual Feis: Syllabus, 1964, 1981-1989, 1997-2001 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Auditors Report, 1987 (Bin 3, Folder 6)
- Community Action Bureau publication: The Needs of the American-Irish Community in the City of New York, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Constitution, 1942, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Constitution, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1976-1991 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Delegates Meetings, Newsletter, 1984-2003 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Grand Festival: Yonkers Raceway, Jun 16, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Installation of Officers, 1975-2007, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Irish Year Book, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Monthly Meeting Notices, 1982-1989, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- New York Irish Feis Day: New York World's Fair, Aug 1, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Rita Fitzpatrick UICA Feis Scrapbook: Annual Celebrations, 1934-1980 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Rita Fitzpatrick UICA Feis Scrapbook: Articles and Personal Notes, 1979, 1996, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Rita Fitzpatrick UICA Feis Scrapbook: Photographs and Newsclippings (photocopies), 1938-1959, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Ephemera: Commemorative Ribbons, 1941-1954 (Box 4)